A curious little invention is being talked about.
اختراع صغير وغريب يجري الحديث عنه.
It's called a microscope.
يدعى بالمجهر.
What it allows you to do
مايسمح لك بالقيام به
is see tiny little lifeforms
هو رؤية الكائنات الحية الصغيرة جداً
that are invisible to the naked eye.
التي لا ترى بالعين المجردة.
Soon comes the medical discovery
بعدها بقليل سيأتي اكتشاف طبي
that many of these lifeforms are actually causes
يظهر أن العديد من هذه الكائنات تشكل سببا
of terrible human diseases.
لأمراض بشرية خطيرة.
Imagine what happened to the society
تخيل ماحدث للمجتمع
when they realized
حينما أدرك
that an English mom in her teacup
أن الأم الانجليزية و في فنجان شايها
actually was drinking a monster soup,
كانت في الواقع تشرب حساء مليئا بالجراثيم.
not very far from here. This is from London.
ليس ببعيد عن هنا. هذه كانت في لندن.
Fast forward 200 years.
بعد 200 سنة.
We still have this monster soup around,
لازالت تلك الجراثيم هذا حولنا
and it's taken hold in the developing countries
ولا زالت تحكم قبضتها على البلدان النامية
around the tropical belt.
حول الحزام الإستوائي.
Just for malaria itself,
بالنسبة للملاريا فقط،
there are a million deaths a year,
هناك مليون حالة وفاة كل سنة،
and more than a billion people
و أكثر من مليار شخص
that need to be tested because they are at risk
بحاجة للتشخيص لأنهم معرضون
for different species of malarial infections.
لأنواع مختلفة من التهابات الملاريا.
Now it's actually very simple to put a face
و الأن، في الحقيقة، من السهل جداً أن نتعرف
to many of these monsters.
على العديد من هذه الجراثيم.
You take a stain, like acridine orange
تأخذ صبغة، على سبيل المثال أكردين البرتقال
or a fluorescent stain or Giemsa,
أوالصبغة الفلورية أو الجميزا،
and a microscope, and you look at them.
و مجهرا، لتنظر إليها.
They all have faces.
تمتلك كلها وجوها.
Why is that so, that Alex in Kenya,
لم لايزال آلكس من كينيا،
Fatima in Bangladesh, Navjoot in Mumbai,
وفاطمة في بنغلادش، و نافجوت في مومباي
and Julie and Mary in Uganda still wait months
و جولي و ماري في أوغندا في الانتظار شهورا
to be able to diagnose why they are sick?
من أجل أن يشخصوا ليعرفوا لم هم مرضى؟
And that's primarily because scalability
وهذا في المقام الأول، بسبب أن قابلية
of the diagnostics is completely out of reach.
التشخيص بعيدة تماماً عن المتناول.
And remember that number: one billion.
و تذكر ذاك الرقم: مليار.
The problem lies with the microscope itself.
المشكله تكمن في المجهر نفسه.
Even though the pinnacle of modern science,
على الرغم من أن العلم الحديث في قمة أوجه،
research microscopes are not designed for field testing.
إلا أنه مجاهر البحث ليست مصممة للاختبارات الميدانية.
Neither were they first designed
حتى أنها لم تكن بالأساس
for diagnostics at all.
مصممة للقيام بالتشخيص إطلاقا.
They are heavy, bulky, really hard to maintain,
فهي ثقيلة، و ضخمة و يصعب الاعتناء بها
and cost a lot of money.
وتكلف الكثير من المال.
This picture is Mahatma Gandhi in the '40s
هذه صورة المهاتما غاندي في الأربعينات
using the exact same setup that we actually use today
وهو يستخدم الطريقة نفسها التي نتسخدمها اليوم
for diagnosing T.B. in his ashram
لتشخيص الملاريا في معبده
in Sevagram in India.
في سفيقرام الهند.
Two of my students, Jim and James,
سافر اثنان من طلبتي، جيم و جيمز،
traveled around India and Thailand,
في أنحاء الهند و تايلند،
starting to think about this problem a lot.
وبدأوا في التفكير في هذه المشكلة كثيراً.
We saw all kinds of donated equipment.
رأينا جميع الأنواع من المعدات المتبرع بها.
We saw fungus growing on microscope lenses.
رأينا فطريات تنمو على عدسات المجهر.
And we saw people who had a functional microscope
ورأينا أشخاصا لديهم مجهر عملي
but just didn't know how to even turn it on.
لكنهم لم يكونوا يعلمون كيف يمكن تشغيله.
What grew out of that work and that trip
ما نتج عن هذا العمل و هذه الرحلة
was actually the idea of what we call Foldscopes.
كان حقيقه الفكرة التي نسميها المجاهر المطوية.
So what is a Foldscope?
ماهو المجهر المطوي؟
A Foldscope is a completely functional microscope,
المجهر المطوي هو مجهر عملي تماماً،
a platform for fluorescence, bright-field,
منصة للاستشعاع و المجال المضيء
polarization, projection,
والاستقطاب،والإسقاط،
all kinds of advanced microscopy
جميع الأنواع المجاهر المتقدمة
built purely by folding paper.
صنعت من ورق مطوي بحت.
So, now you think, how is that possible?
إذا أنتم تفكرون الآن، كيف لهذا أن يكون ممكنا؟
I'm going to show you some examples here,
سأريكم الآن بعض الأمثلة هنا،
and we will run through some of them.
و سوف نتطرق لبعضها بشكل سريع.
It starts with a single sheet of paper.
إنها تبدأ بورقة واحدة.
What you see here is all the possible components
ما ترون هنا هو جميع المكونات الممكنة
to build a functional bright-field and fluorescence microscope.
لبناء مجهر المجال المضيء و مجهر الاستشعاع.
So, there are three stages:
لذا، هنالك ثلاث مراحل:
There is the optical stage, the illumination stage
هنالك المرحلة البصرية، ومرحلة الإضاءة
and the mask-holding stage.
و مرحلة مسك القناع.
And there are micro optics at the bottom
و هنالك بصريات صغيرة في الأسفل
that's actually embedded in the paper itself.
والتي تشكل جزء من الورقة نفسها.
What you do is, you take it on,
ماتقوم به هو أنك تأخذها،
and just like you are playing like a toy,
ومثلما تقوم باللعب بلعبة ما،
which it is,
و هي فعلا كذالك،
I tab it off,
أضغطها،
and I break it off.
و أقوم بفصلها.
This paper has no instructions and no languages.
ليس لهذه الورقة تعلميات أو لغات
There is a code, a color code embedded,
هنالك شفرة، شفرة ملونة مدمجة،
that tells you exactly how to fold that specific microscope.
تخبرك عن كيفية طي ذاك المجهر المحدد.
When it's done, it looks something like this,
حينما يكون جاهزاً، يبدو نوعاً ما كهذا،
has all the functionalities of a standard microscope,
لديه كل وظائف المجهر المثالي.
just like an XY stage,
مثل مرحلة س ص.
a place where a sample slide could go,
مكان حيث يمكن لشريحة عينة أن توضع،
for example right here.
على سبيل المثال هنا،
We didn't want to change this,
لم نرد تغيير هذا،
because this is the standard
لأنه هذا المعيار
that's been optimized for over the years,
الذي تم تحسينه على مدار السنين،
and many health workers are actually used to this.
وقد اعتاد عليه العديد من العاملين في مجال الصحة.
So this is what changes,
لذا هذا ماتغير،
but the standard stains all remain the same
لكن الصبغات المثالية لا تزال كما هي
for many different diseases.
بالنسبة للعديد من الأمراض المختلفة
You pop this in.
تدخلها بسرعة.
There is an XY stage,
هنالك مرحلة س ص،
and then there is a focusing stage,
و بعد ذالك مرحلة التركيز،
which is a flexure mechanism
و التي هي آلية الطي
that's built in paper itself that allows us to move
و التي بنيت في الورقة نفسها لتسمح لنا بتحريك
and focus the lenses by micron steps.
و تركيز العدسات بواسطة خطوات الميكرون.
So what's really interesting about this object,
والمثير حقا بشأن هذا الشيء،
and my students hate when I do this,
وهو مايكره طلبتي أن أقوم به،
but I'm going to do this anyway,
لكني سأقوم بذالك على أي حال،
is these are rugged devices.
هذه أجهزة غليظة.
I can turn it on and throw it on the floor
أستطيع تشغيلها و رميها على الأرض
and really try to stomp on it.
و أحاول حقاً أن أضع قدمي عليها.
And they last, even though they're designed
وهي تدوم طويلاً، على الرغم من أنهم صممت
from a very flexible material, like paper.
من مادة مرنة، مثل الورق.
Another fun fact is, this is what we actually
و حقيقة ممتعة أخرى، إليكم مانقوم فعلا
send out there as a standard diagnostic tool,
بإرساله هناك كأداة تشخيص تقليدية،
but here in this envelope
لكن هنا في هذا الظرف
I have 30 different foldscopes
لدي 30 نوع مختلف من المجاهر المطوية
of different configurations all in a single folder.
من مختلف التكوينات، كلها في في ملف واحد.
And I'm going to pick one randomly.
وسأقوم باختيار واحد عشوائيا.
This one, it turns out, is actually designed
هذا، تبين، أنه صمم
specifically for malaria,
خصيصاً من أجل الملاريا،
because it has the fluorescent filters built
لأنه يحتوي على مرشحات استشعاع
specifically for diagnosing malaria.
صممت خصيصاً لتشخيص الملاريا.
So the idea of very specific diagnostic microscopes
لذا فكرة المجاهر التشخيصية المحددة جداً
comes out of this.
ظهرت من خلال هذا.
So up till now, you didn't actually see
لحد الآن، لم تروا حقاً
what I would see from one of these setups.
ما سأرى من خلال إحدى هذه الأجهزة.
So what I would like to do is,
لذا ما أود القيام به هو،
if we could dim the lights, please,
هلا جعلنا الإضاءة خافتة، رجاء.
it turns out foldscopes are also projection microscopes.
تبين أيضاً أن المجاهر المطوية هي أيضاً مجاهر إسقاط.
I have these two microscopes that I'm going to turn --
لدي هذان المجهران الصغيران اللذان سأقوم بتشغيلهما--
go to the back of the wall --
وسأذهب إلى خلف الحائط--
and just project, and this way you will see
وأعرض فقط، و بهذه الطريقة سترى
exactly what I would see.
تماماً ما سأرى.
What you're looking at --
ما تنظرون إليه--
(Applause) —
(تصفيق)
This is a cross-section of a compound eye,
هذا مقطع عرضي لمجمع عين،
and when I'm going to zoom in closer, right there,
و حينما أكبر الصورة أكثر، هناك،
I am going through the z-axis.
أمر من خلال محور ص.
You actually see how the lenses are cut together
ترون حقيقةً كيف أن العدسات تقطع معاً
in the cross-section pattern.
في نمط عرضي.
Another example, one of my favorite insects,
مثال آخر، واحده من الحشرات المفضلة لدي،
I love to hate this one,
أحب أن أكره هذه،
is a mosquito,
إنها البعوضة،
and you're seeing the antenna of a culex pipiens.
وأنتم ترون هوائي بعوض الكيوليكس.
Right there.
هناك.
All from the simple setup that I actually described.
كل هذا من خلال الإعدادت البسيطة التي وصفتها.
So my wife has been field testing
تقوم زوجتي مؤخراً باختبار ميداني
some of our microscopes
لبعض من مجاهرنا
by washing my clothes whenever I forget them
من خلال غسل ملابسي حينما أنساها
in the dryer.
في آلة التنشيف.
So it turns out they're waterproof, and --
لذا تبين أنها مضادة للماء، و--
(Laughter) —
(ضحك)
right here is just fluorescent water,
هنا لدي ماء الاستشعاع،
and I don't know if you can actually see this.
و لا أعلم حقاً إن كنتم تستطيعون رؤية هذا.
This also shows you how the projection scope works.
و هذا يظهر لكم أيضاً كيف يعمل نطاق الإسقاط .
You get to see the beam the way it's projected and bent.
تسطيع أن ترى الضوء و الطريقة التي من خلالها يعرض و ينحني.
Can we get the lights back on again?
هل لك أن تعيد الإضاءة من فضلك؟
So I'm quickly going to show you,
سأوريكم بشكل سريع،
since I'm running out of time,
خاصهً أنه ليس لدي متسع من الوقت،
in terms of how much it costs for us to manufacture,
من حيث تكلفة التصنيع،
the biggest idea was roll-to-roll manufacturing,
كانت الفكرة الكبرى أن تتم صناعته بطريقة البكرات المتتالية،
so we built this out of 50 cents of parts and costs.
لذا فقد صممناه بتكلفة 50 سنتا تشمل القطع و التكاليف.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And what this allows us to do
و مايمكننا هذا من القيام يه
is to think about a new paradigm in microscopy,
هو التفكير في نموذج جديد في المجاهر
which we call use-and-throw microscopy.
و التي نسميها المجهر" استخدمه و ارمه."
I'm going to give you a quick snapshot
سأعطيكم لمحة سريعة
of some of the parts that go in.
عن بعض القطع التي تستخدمها.
Here is a sheet of paper.
هذه قطعة ورق.
This is when we were thinking about the idea.
هذا كان حينما كنا نفكر في الفكرة.
This is an A4 sheet of paper.
هذه ورقه A4
These are the three stages that you actually see.
هذه المراحل الثلاث التي ترونها.
And the optical components, if you look at the inset up on the right,
و المكونات البصرية، إذا نظرتم إلى المدمج في الأعلى على اليمين،
we had to figure out a way to manufacture lenses
كان يتوجب علينا أن نجد طريقة لتصنيع العدسات
in paper itself at really high throughputs,
في الورقة نفسها بإنتاجية عالية.
so it uses a process of self-assembly
لذا فهو يستخدم عملية التجميع الذاتي
and surface tension
و السطح المضغوط
to build achromatic lenses in the paper itself.
لبناء عدسات لالونية في الورقة نفسها.
So that's where the lenses go.
هنا مكان العدسات.
There are some light sources.
هنالك مصادر للضوء.
And essentially, in the end,
وأساسا، في نهاية المطاف،
all the parts line up because of origami,
كل الأجزاء تصطف على شكل الأورغامي،
because of the fact that origami allows us
لأن الأوريغامي يمكننا من الحصول
micron-scale precision of optical alignment.
على دقة على مستوى نطاق الميكرون للمحاذاة البصرية.
So even though this looks like a simple toy,
بالرغم من أنه يبدو كلعبة بسيطة،
the aspects of engineering that go in
فإن الجوانب الهندسية المستخدمة فيه
something like this are fairly sophisticated.
تعتبر شيئا متطورا إلى حد ما.
So here is another obvious thing that we would do,
هناك أمر واضح آخر ربما نقوم بعمله،
typically, if I was going to show
عادةً، إن أردت أظهر
that these microscopes are robust,
أن هذه المجاهر الصغيرة قوية،
is go to the third floor and drop it from the floor itself.
سأذهب إلى الدور الثالث و أرميها من هناك.
There it is, and it survives.
إنها هناك، وقد نجت.
So for us, the next step actually
لذا فبالنسبة لنا، فالخطوة القادمة
is really finishing our field trials.
هي إنهاء تجاربنا الميدانية
We are starting at the end of the summer.
سنبدأ في نهاية الصيف.
We are at a stage where we'll be making thousands of microscopes.
نحن في مرحلة من خلالها سنقوم بتصنيع آلآف من المجاهر.
That would be the first time where we would be
ستكون تلك المرة الأولى
doing field trials with the highest density
التي سنقوم فيها بتجارب ميدانية بأعلى كثافة
of microscopes ever at a given place.
من المجاهر على الإطلاق في مكان معين.
We've started collecting data for malaria,
بدأنا بجمع بيانات عن الملاريا،
Chagas disease and giardia from patients themselves.
داء داء المثقبيّات الأمريكي والجياردية من المرضى أنفسهم.
And I want to leave you with this picture.
و أريد أن أودعكم بهذه الصورة
I had not anticipated this before,
لمأخطط لهذا من قبل.
but a really interesting link
لكن هناك رابط مثير حقاُ
between hands-on science education
بين المشاركة الفعلية في تعليم العلوم
and global health.
و الصحة العالمية.
What are the tools that we're actually providing
ماهي الأدوات التي نقدمها حقاُ
the kids who are going to fight
للأطفال الذي سيحاربون
this monster soup for tomorrow?
تلك الجراثيم غداً؟
I would love for them to be able to just print out
أحب أن تكون لديهم القدرة على طباعة
a Foldscope and carry them around in their pockets.
المجهر المطوي و حمله معهم في جيوبهم.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)